Ian Githua

- Software Engineer Nairobi, Kenya 254700797003
 - iangithua@gmail.com linkedin.com/in/ian-githua

Accomplished software developer with 5 years in the development of applications. Excels in every stage of the life cycle of software development, including design creation, coding, debugging, testing, and maintenance. Experienced in devising tailored solutions to assist businesses to achieve their goals in a variety of industries. Advanced skills and knowledge of programming tools with a background in data structures and data-processing logic. Authored applications in a scrum team of 6 and improved the processes reducing time to market by 50%. This improves the team's throughput by 60% from development to deployment.

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

e.KRAAL Innovation Hub, Nairobi

Software Engineer

October 2018 - Present

- Reviewed project specifications and prepared technology solutions that met or exceeded performance expectations.
- Participated in architecture, design and implementation of backend feature using Java, Spring boot, Maven and Hibernate.
- Promoted experience with Kubernetes, Docker and Cloud services to meet client requirements for functionality, scalability and performance by 98%.
- Analyzed enhancements and updates for subsystems of end-user applications software running on local, networked and Internet-based platforms.
- Leveraged cross-platform development to reduce time to market by 50%.
- Collaborated with management, internal and development partners regarding software application design status and project progress.
- Came up with robust, scalable, modular and API-centric infrastructures improving 3rd party sharing of data process by 60%.

Sematime Ltd, Nairobi

Software Developer

August 2018 - October 2018

- Wrote clear, clean code utilizing best coding practices ensuring 90% collaboration.
- Engineered modern applications in java with vaadin programming language. This
 helped in supporting development, QA and user experience staff to develop new
 products.

Safaricom PLC, Nairobi

Software Developer Intern

April 2018 - July 2018

- Worked with developers to identify and remove software bugs reducing support traffic by 70%.
- Assisted with testing of client-server network components ensuring 99.9% uptime.

- Maintained first-line support chart platform up and running 99% of the working hours and ensured to have cleared customer queue by 100 % before COB.
- Developed libraries to assist developers in integrations with Safaricom's online payment using <u>C# programming language</u> reducing support traffic by 20%.

EDUCATION

Bachelor of science in computer science, September 2015 – October 2018 Africa Nazarene University, Nairobi

• Result in a second-class upper division with a GPA of 3.483/4.0, acquiring 7 honors and 1 dean's list award.

ACHIEVEMENTS

- Designed an edge-computing architecture to achieve a non-intrusive smart parking solution, winning the Konza technopolis challenge 2021 awarding us the tender for parking solutions at Konza.
- Throughout the next quarter, maintain 99.99% uptime on the platform.
- Take a 6-month course to learn more about a needed technology to be used.
- Spend 2 hours per week mentoring another developer on the team.
- Take responsibility for managing a project in the next quarter, and delivering it on time with 95% customer satisfaction.
- Received the best achiever award from Safaricom PLC out of 40 colleagues.
- Received a GitHub achievement award in 2018 as an Artic code vault contributor from Safaricom PLC for improving developer integrations by 10% without support.

SKILLS

- Problem-solving and teamwork skills.
- Programming languages (Java, C#, PHP, Flutter, JavaScript, HTML, CSS).
- Docker and Kubernetes.
- Excellent organizational and time management skills.
- Accuracy and attention to detail.
- An understanding of the latest trends and their role in a commercial environment.
- Self-development skills to keep up to date with fast-changing trends.

CERTIFICATIONS

- Modern Apps, Serverless Development, Containers, and Cloud Practitioner-Aws.
- Cloud Intro IBM.
- Application Security Analyst Mastery Award for Students 2016 IBM.
- API Design and Fundamentals of Google Cloud's Apigee API Platform (with Honors).
- Scrum Fundamentals Certified.
- API Development on Google Cloud's Apigee API Platform (with Honors).
- API Security on Google Cloud's Apigee API Platform (with Honors)